Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, good morning. Today's דף daf is a
good second day of the עומר. Omer. Today's דף daf is מ"ה.
mem hey. We pick up in the bottom third of מ"ד עמוד
ב', mem daled amud bais, the two dots, lines start with אתמר,
itmar, about 15 lines before the lines get wide. And we have
just had a whole major debate over Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish
about the status of a נערה, na'arah, where the חכמים Chachamim say
she can receive a גט, get, Rabbi Yehuda says even that she
can't do, but then Rabbi Yochanan says that's all she can do
is receive a גט, get, because she's not really, she's passive, it's
not she's making a choice, it's בעל כרחה, b'al karchah, but any
type of a thing that requires her decision, like getting married, that's
all in the power of the father. So even though legally she's
an adult as a נערה, na'arah, all of the real decision and
power for any type of a transaction rests with the father. Now
we shift back to the case of the קטנה, ktanah, which should
be obvious, a קטנה ktanah is not an adult and so clearly
any action she's going to do won't be meaningful, but today's דף
daf and even a little bit of tomorrow's דף daf is going
to deal with a scenario where this קטנה ktanah goes ahead and
decides to marry herself off. Now we would assume that if you
can't do it for a נערה, na'arah, you obviously can't do it
for a קטנה, ktanah, it should be completely meaningless, but we're going
to see some possibility that maybe that has some weight and we'll
see why. And just so people should realize this is not purely
a speculative thing, it does sound a little absurd, here what this
10 year old is going to decide on her own to marry
herself off, to elope, but actually when the גמרא Gemara gets into
the discussion to ends the
סוגיא, sugya, ראשונים Rishonim get into a very heated discussion about how
do we פסקן, pasken, because apparently cases like this would happen. Now
I'm not exactly sure if it was the girl on her own,
but certainly cases where the father wasn't around, the father was overseas,
מדינת הים medinas hayam for some extended period of time and maybe
the mother decided to marry the girl off, right? So she was
young and they, you know, they dealt at the beginning of this
פרק. perek. תוספות Tosafos told us that even though the גמרא Gemara
says that a man shouldn't marry off his daughter until she grows
up and she's able to say she wants to marry this guy,
nevertheless תוספות Tosafos pointed out that there was a, you know, a
economic historical reality that created a necessity to marry them off at
a young age even before they were בת מצווה, bas mitzvah, so
that would have been true in cases when the father wasn't around,
even though he was alive. Okay, so this is going to become
a very practical question, let's take a look. אתמר. itmar.
This is assuming the father was dead? Would that be different?
No, dead is different. Dead חז"ל Chazal were מתקן metaken that the
mother and the brothers have the right to marry her off, maybe,
we'll talk about that. But this is a case where the father
is alive. So there's no question the father is really the only
one who has control. Okay, אתמר, itmar, so it was taught: קטנה
שנתקדשה שלא לדעת אביה, ktanah sheniskadshah shelo l'da'as aviha,
a קטנה ktanah that gets married without her father's acquiescence or even
knowledge. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, צריכה גט וצריכה מיאון. tzrichah get v'tzrichah
mi'un.
She needs both a גט get and מיאון. mi'un. Now מיאון mi'un
is strange because מיאון mi'un is only when the mother and the
brothers marry her off. Okay, what's מיאון mi'un doing at all here?
And why do you need both? Why do you even, why certainly
do you need a גט? get? She was only a קטנה. ktanah.
Before the other, right exactly,
I mean what's מיאון mi'un at all and if you do need
it why should you need it together with a גט? get? Normally
מיאון mi'un is instead of a גט. get. מיאון mi'un is like
קידושי דרבנן. kidushei d'rabbanan. So if you wanted to call this some
type of a קידושי דרבנן kidushei d'rabbanan just do מיאון mi'un and
not a גט. get. What's going on here? So that's exactly what
the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר קרנא, Amar
Karna, says קרנא, Karna, name of a חכם: Chacham: דברים בגו, devarim
b'go, there's like things inside here, literally means things are inside here,
meaning there's some problems going on here.
בגו b'go is how you read it?
Okay, דברים בגו, devarim b'go, there's some issues here. What are the
issues? אם
גט למה מיאון אם מיאון למה גט, im get lama mi'un im
mi'un lama get, if one why the other, right? מיאון mi'un is
for a דרבנן d'rabbanan marriage, גט get is for a דאורייתא d'oraisa
marriage, what's going on here? אמרו ליה, amru lei, the Rabbis of
the בית מדרש Beis Medrash said to him: מר עוקבא ובי דינא
בכפרי. Mar Ukva u'vei dina b'Kafri. So look, if you have a
problem with שמואל's Shmuel teaching, מר עוקבא Mar Ukva and his בית
דין beis din are over there in כפרי, Kafri, which apparently is
a nearby town, let's go ask them to explain it. Okay, so
presumably they went there and what did this בית דין beis din
do? This בית דין beis din referred it up. So it says,
or it seems like this is what the בית דין beis din
did, it could be this is also what the Rabbis did. So
what they did is the following: אפכוה
שדרוה לקמיה דרב. afchuha shadroha lekamei d'Rav. They reversed who said what
and they sent it to רב. Rav. Like this is like an
example of blind review. Okay, they didn't want to make sure they
got a non-biased response or at least קרנא Karna would be satisfied.
You know so if רב Rav is going to come and defend
a position of שמואל, Shmuel, קרנא Karna would say, yeah you know
it's his colleague, of course he's defending the position of שמואל. Shmuel.
So they reversed it. They said that קרנא Karna said that she
needs a גט get and מיאון, mi'un, and שמואל, Shmuel, you know,
said it doesn't make sense, one or the other. And let's see
what how רב Rav responds, which one he sides with. Okay, so
they stacked the deck in favor of קרנא's Karna critique. On purpose?
On purpose. They stacked the deck in favor of קרנא's Karna critique
and let's see what רב Rav says. שדרוה לקמיה דרב. shadroha lekamei
d'rav. אמר אמרו להו, amar amru lehu, so רב Rav said back,
הי אלהים, Hai Elohim, like you know, in God's name, צריכה גט
וצריכה מיאון. tzricha get vetzricha miun. No, if שמואל Shmuel questioned that
idea that you need both, it's not true, you do need
both! וחס ליה לזרעיה דאבא בר אבא vechas lei lezarei d'abba bar
abba and God forbid the son, the child of אבא בר אבא,
Abba bar Abba, meaning אבא Abba was שמואל's Shmuel father's name. Okay,
so אבא בר אבא Abba bar Abba was a way of referring
to שמואל. Shmuel. And anyway, God forbid that שמואל Shmuel should say
it, should question that you need both. Okay, so it was very
clear that רב Rav was of the opinion that you need both,
and even when he thought that שמואל Shmuel said the opposite, he
still said you needed both and he couldn't believe that שמואל Shmuel
would say the opposite. So it's רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel now
both very strongly feel that this girl needs both and it doesn't
seem to make any sense.
It's very smart, it's very smart actually of them to do that
on purpose because it could intimidate, like, שמואל Shmuel said that? Oh,
I'm going to second-guess my opinion. He stayed with his opinion, it's
very hard to do that.
Right.
Exactly. Yep. Okay. So וטעמא מאי? v'taama mai? So now רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel both say she needs both. What's going on here?
What's the reason? אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא, Amar Rav Acha
brei d'Rav Ika, צריכה גט, tzricha get, שמא ניתרצה האב. shema nitratza
ha'av. She needs a גט get because maybe the father in the
end will be okay with it. And one minute, well when he
finds out. So one minute. וצריכה מיאון, vetzricha miun, שמא לא ניתרצה
האב בקדושין. shema lo nitratza ha'av bekiddushin. He wouldn't be okay with
it.
But then what's going to happen? She's going to have a גט
get in something that was never a
קידושין. kiddushin. ויאמרו, אין קידושין תופסין באחותה. veyomru ein kiddushin tofsin b'achota
People will say, look, if all we saw was a גט, get,
it must be, people will say, that the father was okay with
it, it was a קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin d'oraisa. The גט get makes
her a גרושה דאורייתא. grusha d'oraisa. And then there's a problem because
then they'll say that if this same man
who gave her the גט get tries to marry her sister, they'll
say it won't be חל chal because you can't marry a woman's
sister even after you divorce the woman as long as the first
wife is still alive. So
basically they're saying ויאמרו veyomru, אין קידושין תופסין באחותה ein kiddushin tofsin
b'achota. means that there are some possible קולות kulot that will emerge
from the fact that people think that this woman is a גרושה
דאורייתא, grusha d'oraisa, a ודאי גרושה. vadai grusha. So they give a
מיאון miun as a way of signaling, you know, maybe that גט
get was only a חומרה. chumra. Because if she was really married,
you don't need anything in addition to a גט. get. So the
fact that they require a מיאון miun shows ממה נפשך, mima nafshach,
maybe it wasn't really דאורייתא d'oraisa married and maybe the גט get
was some חומרה chumra and that therefore it protects us from some
קולא kula that could emerge from assuming she was married דאורייתא, d'oraisa,
which would mean now that the man would not have any, like,
if he even if he gave money to her sister we would
say it wouldn't be חל. chal. Now we realize it might be
חל chal because he was never married to her. So what you
have is two things. Number one is you have the מיאון miun
functions as a way of signaling, not just as a way of
addressing קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin d'rabbanan, which is exactly, you know, this whole
case is an underage girl who gets married without the father. It
looks like קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin d'rabbanan. Right? It looks like the case
when a girl, an underage girl, doesn't have a father and the
mother and the brothers marry her off. So the normal type of
way of responding to that is מיאון. miun. So it doesn't seem
like they just grabbed מיאון miun out of thin air. It seems
like מיאון miun would sort of be a normal way of responding
to something that a case that looks just like this, a קידושין
דרבנן. kiddushin d'rabbanan. Okay, but here they're using
it to balance the possibility that they demanded a גט get and
to signal the fact that this is not really clearly a קידושין
דאורייתא, kiddushin d'oraisa, it's just really like a חשש chashash and a
concern and you know that because we're also demanding מיאון. miun. Now
there's the ראשונים rishonim have a very, one minute, the ראשונים rishonim
have a very, you know, significant discussion about what is this issue
of ניתרצה האב. nitratza ha'av. You know, there's two questions. Question number
one is, even if the father was okay with it, let's say
he was even okay with it from the get-go, how do you
give the money to this girl?
She's a minor, she can't be a שליח. shaliach. Like you can't
give money directly to her, right? So how does that work for
קידושין kiddushin even if the father from the very outset said he
was okay with it? So interestingly, I looked through many many ראשונים
rishonim don't even address the question. Finally the ריטב"א Ritva raises the
question and what he says is, remember at the beginning of the
מסכת masechet where somebody could say, a woman could say to a
man, put the money on that rock there or throw the money
out to the ocean or give the money to that other person
and I'll treat that as my כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. And we
sort of say that that works basically because she gets הנאה hana'ah
that he listens to her or somehow it works through other ways.
Anyway, so even though the girl isn't a שליח, shaliach, if the
father's okay that this giving the money to her counts as כסף
קידושין, kesef kiddushin, that should count as an act of קידושין. kiddushin.
Although again, it's a you know, it's questionable, but that's how we
are explaining it. But the other big question is... But the other
big question comes, when are we concerned that the אב Av was
okay with it? Were we thinking that the אב Av maybe from
the outset
presumed, like was okay, like knew this guy was interested in marrying
his daughter? From the outset was thinking like, yeah, if he gives
money to her I'll be okay with it, or some type of
a thing of that nature? Right? That doesn't sound like them. We
haven't discussed that, although we'll discuss a similar scenario in a minute.
Or the way most, that's what the ראב"ד Ra'avad says, but it
doesn't fit with most of the cases. The way most ראשונים Rishonim
say is when the father eventually, when she comes back and tells
the father, "Oh, this guy gave me this קידושין Kiddushin money," then
maybe he's okay with it. So the question is, what do you
mean maybe he's okay with it? Let's see what his reaction is
then. If he says, "No," if he says, "What are you talking
about? I object," then it's no good. If he says he's okay
with it, then assuming that he could be okay later, he says
he's okay. What do you mean maybe he's okay? So they have
to construct a scenario that she goes back and tells the father
and the father doesn't say anything initially. He's silent. So if he's
silent, we don't know what he's thinking. And then maybe a day
later or ten minutes later he says, "You know, I object." So
the question is, is this objection something new and initially your silence
indicated that you were okay with it, or maybe this objection indicates
that you never were okay with it? So like they construct a
whole scenario that's not in the גמרא. Gemorah. Like when was that
moment that the father became aware and we think that he might
have been okay? And even if he is okay later, why does
it work for something that was done in the past? Right? So
like, and they again they have to say, well maybe since he's
okay with it and he doesn't have to give the money back,
now that he's okay with it when he finds out an hour
later, now the money that's in her pocket, that becomes כסף קידושין.
Kesef Kiddushin. Like it becomes... it seems very, very far-fetched, right? I
mean not even far-fetched to think that maybe he is okay with
it, but to think you have the appropriate mechanics to allow it
to be an act of קידושין. Kiddushin. So it really does seem
very דרבנן Derabbanan and a חשש. Chashash. It's hard to understand what
exactly is the concern and we'll see, we're going to have a
position that completely rejects this.
Yes. I'm not understanding what the point of מיאון Meiun is. We
don't want him marrying his sister and then just give her a
גט, Get, you can't marry your sister.
No, no, no, no. We're afraid that he'll think that if he
were to marry the sister it wouldn't be חל, chal, but it
might be חל chal because it probably isn't a good קידושין דאורייתא
Kiddushin D'Oraisa and it isn't a good גט דאורייתא. Get D'Oraisa.
So therefore we
give, to signal that it wasn't... it was only a very questionable
קידושין Kiddushin and a גט, Get, you do a מיאון. Meiun. So
he knows that if he gives כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin to the
sister, the sister is ספק מקודשת Safek Mekudeshes as opposed to ודאי
אינה מקודשת. Vaday Ino Mekudeshes.
Okay, so the sister is ספק מקודשת, Safek Mekudeshes, so wouldn't גמרא
Gemorah just tell him just don't marry the sister, forget about this
whole thing?
Wait, don't tell him, whatever. They were afraid that people would draw
the wrong inferences, you know. They'd say, "Oh there's a גט, Get,
that must mean X, Y." It's sort of like your classic safeguard.
It's done to signal to protect against other... there are going to
be other cases, you know. תוספות Tosafos discusses, how about marrying a
daughter? How about marrying the mother? How about whatever. A lot of
possible scenarios, you want to signal... you don't want to send confusing
signals. If all you had was a גט, Get, it would signal
to people that this was קידושין דאורייתא. Kiddushin D'Oraisa. Okay. But anyway,
very hard to understand where, at what stage is the father we
think he's being מתרצה, misratzeh, what is the mechanics, where's the כסף
קידושין Kesef Kiddushin coming later, why is it the fact that she
has כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin acceptable if she's not an adult. You
have all of these problems. Anyway, this is the position and the
irony is or the interesting thing is that both רב Rav and...
רב Rav was like shocked that שמואל Shmuel could have said anything
less than she required both. Right? But also to me, at least
to me, it's very hard to understand why any of this is
necessary. Yes.
Is he allowed to marry the sister?
Is he allowed... no, because it might be that it was good
קידושין, Kiddushin, right? Okay, but we don't want him to think that
if he gives כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin he doesn't have to be
concerned about it because it might have been not good קידושין. Kiddushin.
All right, so the גמרא Gemorah says like this,
אמר רב נחמן והוא ששידכו. Amar Rav Nachman V'hu Sheshidchu. So רב
נחמן Rav Nachman tries to limit this. All of this is only
if שידוכין Shidduchin preceded this whole thing. There was all conversation with
the groom and the groom's family, "Do you want to marry my
daughter? Whatever," and the father was there and he was part of
it. And then there was some כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin given not
in the father's presence. All right, that already makes a lot more
sense. Again, not to solve the mechanics so much but at least
to solve like why we would think the father would implicitly agree
to that as a מעשה קידושין, Ma'aseh Kiddushin, maybe even before the
fact. עולא אמר אפילו מיאון אינה צריכה. Ulla Amar Afilu Meiun Ein
Tzricha. You know what? She doesn't even need מיאון. Meiun. Nothing means
anything here. She's a קטנה, ktana, give me a break. No מיאון,
Meiun, no גט, Get, no nothing. Now the גמרא Gemorah says אף
על גב דשידכו? Af Al Gav Deshidchu? The question how to read
this line but I'll read it the way רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafos do. What? Does עולא Ulla mean it's not a problem even
if there were שידוכין Shidduchin that preceded it?
So the גמרא Gemorah says no, מאן דמתני הא לא מתני הא.
man demasni ha lo masni ha. The one that says that we're
talking about a scenario of שידוכין Shidduchin does not say that עולא
Ulla says you don't need מיאון. Meiun. Because according to this way...
If it really were שידכו, shidduchu, then at least עולא Ulla would
agree there's some concern going on here, maybe at least מיאון. miun.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, but some say, אמר עולא, amar Ulla, קטנה
שנתקדשה שלא לדעת אביה אפילו מיאון לא צריכה, ketanah shenitkadshah shelo l'da'at
aviha afilu miun lo tzericha, he said it as an independent statement
and again there's some question how to read this, but the way
רש"י Rashi reads it is that even with
שידוכין, shidduchin, black and white she does not require מיאון, miun, you
don't need anything. So you go from needing both, I mean needing
both is really starting by needing a גט get and then needing
a מיאון miun to counterbalance the message sent by the גט, get,
okay, but that's a but at least to try to limit that
a little bit to a case of שידכו, shidduchu, okay, to עולא
Ulla that says basically you don't need anything. And it's important to
establish that עולא Ulla might the second statement might mean you don't
need anything even with שידכו shidduchu because I'll just, I don't want
to ruin the surprise but I'll go ahead and ruin it. According
to most ראשונים Rishonim we rule against רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel and
she doesn't need a גט get and she doesn't need מיאון miun
and the question is well what about a case of שידכו, shidduchu,
would that be different? So it's important to establish at least a
reading of עולא Ulla that when עולא Ulla rejects them he rejects
them even in a case of שידכו, shidduchu, that you don't require
anything. Yes.
Yes, so שידכו shidduchu like שידוכין shidduchin have some legal import, right?
Well, not on themselves, they create a context for what other things
might happen. שידוכין shidduchin don't do anything by themselves, but that just
sets the scene so that it makes us question what the דעת
da'at was when a certain event happened. Think about a case of
like עוסקין באותו ענין. oskin b'oto inyan. You're עוסקין באותו ענין, oskin
b'oto inyan, you're talking about getting married and then you give a
ring without saying anything, so we can say implicitly that would be
even though nothing was said we understand that that was given על
דעת קידושין. al da'at kiddushin. So it's not that the discussion has
legal weight in itself, it creates a context for us to understand
later action, right? And therefore how do you know what's the implicit
meaning of that later action.
She's standing under the חופה chuppah he doesn't say הרי את מקודשת
לי. harei at mekudeshet li. Yeah, yeah.
It's actually it's actually could be worse if he says the wrong
thing than not saying anything, okay. I could tell you some stories
about that but anyway, moving on, okay. Exactly. Moving on. Okay. מתיבי
רב כהנא, metivei Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked. וכולן אם
מתו או מיאנו או נתגרשו או שנמצאו אילונית צרותיהן מותרות. v'chulan im
metu o mianu o nitgarshu o shenimtzu ailonit tzaroteihen mutarot.
Now
you see, you can never get away from יבמות. Yevamot. Okay, so
remember the case of צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. A guy dies, the
brother here has a couple of wives,
the surviving brother is related to one of those wives. Let's say
it's his daughter, alright, or it's his other scenarios, but let's say
it's his daughter, right, because his daughter could be married to his
brother, that would be her her uncle, okay? So now because he
obviously can't do יבום yibum with his daughter, that's an ערווה, ervah,
he can't do he doesn't do יבום yibum with any of the
co-wives, he doesn't even need חליצה, chalitzah, everybody just walks away. Okay,
that's the opening משנה mishnah in יבמות. Yevamot. Now let's say however
that before his brother died, so before ראובן Reuven died who was
married to שמעון's Shimon daughter,
ראובן Reuven divorced the daughter, or right or what's the other case?
וכולן אם מתו, v'chulan im metu, or the daughter died, okay. So
you
have ראובן, Reuven, here's שמעון, Shimon, okay, he's married to בת שמעון.
bat Shimon.
Sorry, she doesn't get a name. Okay, we'll call her רחל. Rachel.
Okay. Anyway, so if ראובן Reuven dies and then he's married to
other people, okay, דבורה Devorah and אביגיל, Avigail, a lot of other
women. Okay, so anyway if ראובן Reuven dies because because it's his
marriage because he's because he's an ערווה ervah everybody goes off free.
But if before ראובן Reuven died רחל Rachel died or before ראובן
Reuven died רחל Rachel was divorced and she was out of the
picture, then obviously he has to do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitzah
with the remaining wives. Okay, that's the משנה. mishnah. Okay. So וכולן
אם מתו, v'chulan im metu, if these ערוות ervot died, או מיאנו,
o mianu, or let's say it was only a דרבנן d'rabanan that
she was married to ראובן Reuven and then she did מיאון, miun,
okay, and we're going to have to discuss what's that scenario. או
נתגרשו, o nitgarshu, or she was divorced from ראובן, Reuven, או שנמצאו
אילונית, o shenimtzu ailonit, or she turned out she was an אילונית
ailonit and never able to have children and therefore it was a
קידושי טעות, kiddushei ta'ut, צרותיהן מותרות, tzaroteihen mutarot, their co-wives are permissible
meaning and you can do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitzah with the
co-wives. Now, now we want to understand what is the case of
that of מיאון, miun, right? שמעון, Shimon, here she is, right, she
is married to ראובן. Reuven. Now in a case now could be
she married herself to ראובן Reuven as an adult, right, רחל Rachel
here. Everybody with me? I mean naturally, yeah, to ראובן. Reuven. But
מיאון miun only works when a girl is a קטנה. ketanah. Okay,
so how did she get married to ראובן Reuven with a קידושין
דרבנן kiddushin d'rabanan and then מיאון miun is the relevant way of
walking away if שמעון Shimon is still alive? Okay, normally מיאון miun
is only when שמעון Shimon is dead and the mother and the
brothers marry her off. He was on the... okay, so וכולן אם
מתו... v'chulan im metu... so the גמרא Gemara says... דקא צמת מאן—in
d'ka tsamat man this case, who married off this daughter? אילימא דקדשה
אביה—the Ilima d'kadshah aviha father? במיאון סגי לה? b'Miun sagi lah? How
does she walk away with מיאון? Miun? גט מעליא בעי—she Get ma'alya
ba'ei needs a real גט. Get. אלא לאו דקדשה אינפשה? Ela lav
d'kadshah inafshah? So she must be she married herself
off. וקתני דבעיא מיאון—and v'katani d'ba'ya Miun you see that she requires
מיאון. Miun. So how could עולא Ulla say she requires nothing? Now
in a way, this could be a question of רב ושמואל Rav
v'Shmuel as well, because it sounds like she only required מיאון; Miun;
she didn't also require a גט. Get. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot deals
with that, but what you see is there are scenarios where a
daughter—a girl underage could marry herself off and at least it's some
rabbinic problem that at least we demand מיאון. Miun. Okay, and in
a way it should also be a question to רב ושמואל Rav
v'Shmuel because it doesn't demand גט. Get. But anyway, do you have
a scenario that a daughter can have a father and be underage
and demand מיאון? Miun? So the גמרא Gemara says, הוא מותיב לה
והוא מפרק לה—he hu motev lah v'hu mefarek lah raised this question
and he answered it: כגון שנעשתה לה מעשה יתומה בחיי אביה. k'gon
she-na'asta lah ma'aseh yetoma b'chayei aviha. She was—she was treated like an
orphan in her father's life. What does that mean? So—so
basically what it means is is that this was her second marriage,
נבעך, nebach, this young girl. First she was married to some other
guy, okay, by the father, קידושין, Kiddushin, and not only that, there
was נישואין Nisuin to the other guy, and then the other guy
died, okay. So now this—you can have—you can have
an emancipated minor. You know how you have an emancipated minor? Well,
this girl is—is that she was married to another guy, and with
נישואין, Nisuin, and then she completely leaves the father's control because of
נישואין, Nisuin, and then the other guy dies or divorces her.
She's under twelve years old and there was נישואין? Nisuin?
Yes. And then the other guy dies or divorces her. Now she
has completely left the father's control because of נישואין, Nisuin, so she's
no longer under the father's control. So then she married herself off
to ראובן. Reuven. That would require מיאון. Miun. Now why that's important
is it helps us understand the role that מיאון Miun is doing
here. Because again, classic מיאון Miun is there's no father and the
mother or the brothers marry her off and the חז"ל Chazal instituted
a קידושין דרבנן. Kiddushin d'Rabanan. What we are sort of saying is
there could be other scenarios where this underage girl is married but
not married דאורייתא, d'Oraita, and we will recognize it to a certain
degree and require מיאון Miun the same way when her mother and
brothers would marry her off. So one scenario is: no mother and
brothers, there's no father—or she's an emancipated minor, so if she's out
of her father's control she's out of her mother and brothers' control,
right, because she went ahead and like had totally got married to
another guy—so all of her family is irrelevant to her, and she
goes ahead and marries herself off. That's just like her mother and
brothers married her off as a minor and that would require מיאון.
Miun. So a similar case is that there is a father and
she's marrying herself off, right? Does that become a type of a
קידושין דרבנן Kiddushin d'Rabanan that requires a מיאון? Miun? So that's the
issue. The גט Get idea is—is a more extreme concern that maybe
the father said okay and it became a קידושין דאורייתא. d'Oraita. But
the מיאון Miun idea is patterned after that basic idea of when
there's mother and brothers and no fathers and she's a minor, it's
קידושין דרבנן. Kiddushin d'Rabanan. So you could have other cases: you could
have she's emancipated because she had been married to another guy and
she married herself off, or she married herself off without her father's
okay. Do those create a type of a קידושין דרבנן Kiddushin d'Rabanan
to require a מיאון? Miun? So in the first case we said
yes, that's what's going on by this case of יבום—she Yibum had
been emancipated and married herself off. But our focus is: there is
a father around, will that ever require מיאון Miun and/or a גט?
Get?
Okay, I'm sure Rashi says that the מיאון Miun is to protect
her from being treated like a הפקר hefker because she's so young?
No. And did they give her
a מעמד ma'amad of—of being like a יתומה? yetoma? Right, so this
is דקטנה שאין לה אב שלא ינהגו בה מנהג הפקר. d'ketana she-ein
lah av she-lo yinhagu bah minhag hefker.
No,
that's why they made the establishment of the—of the קידושין דרבנן. Kiddushin
d'Rabanan. Wait a minute. Sorry,
let me... no, no,
no, that's not the מיאון. Miun. That's why they had—they instituted the
whole קידושין דרבנן Kiddushin d'Rabanan when there wasn't a father. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, so הוא מותיב לה
והוא מפרק לה. hu motev lah v'hu mefarek lah. Okay, מיתיבי רב
המנונא. meitivei Rav Hamnuna. So רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna asked: אין מוכרה
לקרובים. ein mocherah l'krovim. Do
you remember this? This is about the father selling his daughter off
as a slave. So he cannot sell her to relatives, because the
whole purpose of selling her as a slave, as a Hebrew slave,
is to lead to the ייעוד. yi'ud. So if he sold her
to a relative, there can't be any ייעוד, yi'ud, there can't be
any קידושין. Kiddushin.
Like to ראובן? Reuven?
No, no, well, a relative that there's no קידושין Kiddushin with. Okay.
Like his brother? Yeah, exactly. משום רבי אליעזר אמרו מוכרה לקרובים. mishum
Rabi Eliezer amru mocherah l'krovim. רבי
אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says no, it's okay, you can have שפחות shifchut
without being a possibility of ייעוד. yi'ud. Okay, ושוין שמוכר אלמנה לכהן
גדול גרושה... v'shavin she-mocher almana l'chohen gadol grusha... גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט.
grusha vechaluza lekohen hedyot.
He can sell her to somebody that maybe there's, it's אסור assur
to do קידושין, kiddushin, but קידושין kiddushin could be חל. chal. Okay,
that would not be excluded, categorically excluded from ייעוד. yiud. So he
can't sell to like his father, okay, because that's the father's granddaughter,
but he can sell to a if she's an אלמנה almana or
she's a גרושה, grusha, can sell her to a כהן kohen because
there, even though קידושין kiddushin is אסור assur there, it would be
חל, chal, so it's not seen like it's off the table and
therefore he can sell her as a שפחה. shifcha.
Now if she's an אלמנה, almana, he'd be allowed to do that,
right? What? If she's an אלמנה, almana, then she's married and
he, I thought he loses all rights to her once she's an
אלמנה. almana.
Well, we're going to discuss that. Not if she's an אלמנה almana
from the אירוסין. eirusin. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now, האי אלמנה, hai almana, but that's exactly what we're going to
ask. Here this daughter selling off, this guy's selling off his daughter
who's an אלמנה. almana. היכי דמי? heichi dami? How did she become
an אלמנה? almana? אילימא דקידשה אביה, ilima dekidsha aviha, so he married
her, it was only אירוסין, eirusin, so she's still under his control
and then the חתן chosson died, now she's an אלמנה. almana. So
now he's going to go ahead and sell her as a שפחה
shifcha to some other man. So if that's the case, מי מצי
מזבין לה? mi matzi mazbin lah? How can he sell her? הא
אין אדם מוכר את בתו לשפחה אחר אישות. ha ein adam mocher
es bito leshifcha achar ishus. You, right, there's different opinions about this
about whether he can sell her as a שפחה shifcha twice, etc.,
but anyway the opinion the גמרא Gemara takes as the פסק psak
is once he's married her, he's no longer allowed to sell her
as a שפחה. shifcha. Okay? So therefore, if he had married her
off קידושי דאורייתא kiddushei d'Oraisa and then the husband died, now and
now she's an אלמנה, almana, now we can discuss marrying her off
to a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Okay, how could we have that
discussion? He's not allowed to sell her off.
How old is this girl?
Under twelve. Okay. Otherwise he couldn't be selling her and marrying her.
אלא לאו דקדשה היא נפשה. ella lav dekidsha hi nafsha. It must
be you could have a scenario where he had not married her,
but she somehow had married herself. Okay? You got the case? Meaning
in order for him to be selling her as a שפחה shifcha
and she's an אלמנה almana or a גרושה, grusha, if we assume
he can't sell her after he married her off, then the only
way she could have been previously married and there's a father here,
it's not like the father is dead, right, the only way this
minor could have been previously married with there being a father and
the father has not married her himself had not married her, would
only be if she had married herself off. So you see it's
possible for a girl, an underage girl who marries herself off, that
at least it's קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin d'Rabbanan. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא לאו דקדשה היא נפשה, ella lav dekidsha hi nafsha, she
married herself off, וקא קרי לה אלמנה, veka kari lah almana, and
you're calling her an אלמנה. almana. You could ask the same question
about גרושה. grusha. אמר רב עמרם אמר רב יצחק, amar Rav Amram
amar Rav Yitzchak, הכא בקידושי ייעוד ואליבא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, hacha
bekiddushei yiud va'aliba deRabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר מעות הראשונות לאו לקידושין
ניתנו. d'amar maos harishonos lav lekiddushin nitnu. Okay,
so that should all be clear because we learned that before. So
no, what it means is, here's what happened. He didn't marry her
off before, it is קידושי דאורייתא, kiddushei d'Oraisa, but he didn't marry
her off directly. First he sold her to guy number one. Okay?
And guy number one did ייעוד yiud with her, turned that sale
into קידושין. kiddushin. And then guy number one died or divorced her.
So now she's an אלמנה almana or a גרושה. grusha. Now he
wants to go ahead and sell her to guy number two. So
you say, well, you're not allowed, you can't sell her after you
already married her once before. So he says, I didn't marry her
off once before, I sold her once before. So I can sell
her a second time after selling her a first time. I can't
sell her after marrying her off, but I can sell her after
selling her. Okay, so קידושי ייעוד kiddushei yiud means the first marriage
came through a sale, not directly through קידושין. kiddushin. And then the
guy died or divorced. What? But it ended in marriage, he did
ייעוד. yiud. Okay, he sold her to guy number one, guy number
one actually did ייעוד yiud and turned it into a קידושין. kiddushin.
And then guy number one died, so she's an אלמנה דאורייתא, almana
d'Oraisa, or guy number one divorced her, she's a גרושה דאורייתא. grusha
d'Oraisa. But it came through ייעוד, yiud, not through קידושין. kiddushin.
ייעוד Yiud would imply נישואין? nisuin?
Well, ייעוד yiud is turning the כסף מכירה kessef mechira into, no,
wouldn't be נישואין nisuin because because she's still under the father's control,
it's אירוסין. eirusin. He turned the כסף מכירה kessef mechira into כסף
קידושין. kessef kiddushin. Okay, well actually we'll see what he did in
a minute. But he turns a מכירה mechira into a קידושין. kiddushin.
Alright, everybody got the case? He sold her to guy number one.
So now, now he can sell her to guy number two because
that's
שפחה אחר שפחה, shifcha achar shifcha, it's not שפחה אחר אישות, shifcha
achar ishus, because the first sale had started off as a sale
of her as a שפחה, shifcha, not as a sale of her
as an אישות.
ishus. And even through ייעוד yiud it's still not considered אישות? ishus?
Exactly. Because the father didn't do that. The, right.
So
בקידושי ייעוד ואליבא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, bekiddushei yiud va'aliba deRabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר מעות הראשונות לאו לקידושין ניתנו. d'amar maos harishonos lav
lekiddushin nitnu. When the first guy who bought her turned it into
קידושין, kiddushin, did ייעוד, yiud, it did not turn the original money
that had been paid to the father into כסף קידושין, kessef kiddushin,
because then retroactively we would say that the father had been מקדש
mekadesh her. What it did was, he was מקדש mekadesh her with
the remainder of the service that she owed him. Okay, so people
get this? So here we have,
okay. ראובן Reuven goes ahead and we'll just call it guy one
and guy two, guy number one and guy number two. So to
guy number one he goes ahead and sells her as a שפחה.
shifcha. Okay.
Then guy number one does ייעוד. yeed. So now it's קידושין דאורייתא.
kiddushin d'oraisa. That becomes קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin d'oraisa. קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin d'oraisa,
okay? Then guy number one dies or divorces her, so now she
becomes a גרושה grusha or an אלמנה דאורייתא. almana d'oraisa. Okay? אלמנה
דאורייתא. almana d'oraisa. And now this guy number two happens to be
a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, okay, a כהן kohen or a כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, okay. So now ראובן, Reuven, since it was only
קידושין, kiddushin, she's still a קטנה, ktana, there was never נישואין, nisuin,
she goes back to being under ראובן'ס Reuven's control, okay, and then
now ראובן Reuven goes ahead and ראובן Reuven now marries her off
to guy number two, so that's a case of אלמנה almana to
a כהן גדול kohen gadol or he sells...
No, marries her.
So and he's allowed to do it because it's קידושין kiddushin after
שפחות. shifchus. Okay. He first sold her as a שפחה shifcha and
now she goes back to him and he's marrying her off, she's
still a minor, that's קידושין kiddushin after שפחות. shifchus. But that only
is true if this does not retroactively turn into an act of
קידושין. kiddushin. So when he does ייעוד, yeed, if the ייעוד yeed
would turn this money that was given—because when he sold her as
a שפחה shifcha he paid money, right? He paid money.
So if the ייעוד yeed would turn that into an act of
קידושין, kiddushin, then it would be... then the...
I'm sorry, he doesn't do קידושין... kiddushin. excuse me, I said קידושין
kiddushin to guy number two. Excuse me. Sold her as a שפחה
shifcha to guy number two. Okay. So, but it's a שפחות shifchus
that has an איסור קידושין. issur kiddushin. Okay, anyway, so if this
turned this into... if when he does ייעוד yeed this turned this
money into כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, he couldn't sell her as a
שפחה shifcha because it's שפחה shifcha after קידושין. kiddushin. So but if
we say it's not the original money that becomes כסף קידושין, kesef
kiddushin, when he does ייעוד, yeed, what he's basically saying is: you
still owe me a year of service, let's take that year of
service and I'll accept that year of service as כסף קידושין, kesef
kiddushin, as it were, then the act of קידושין kiddushin. comes later
and therefore this is a case of שפחות shifchus after שפחות, shifchus,
not שפחות shifchus after קידושין.
kiddushin, So in other words, guy number one says to her, instead
of making kugel all year in the kitchen as my שפחה, shifcha,
make the same kugel in the kitchen all year as my wife.
There you go, exactly. Okay. Anyway, bottom line is that what we're
saying here
is that this case, what the important thing is is that
the idea is: can you take this concept of מיאון miun of
קידושין דרבנן kiddushin d'rabbanan and transfer it to cases where it's not
the mother and brother marrying off this minor? Other cases of a
minor being married. So one case is she marries herself off when
she's emancipated, that we discussed. And the other case is she marries
herself off when there is a father. How much does that require
מיאון? miun? So the
גמרא Gemara is... עולא Ulla is resisting the evidence that there would
ever be a case of מיאון miun if there is a father.
If there is a father, then what she does is meaningless, you
certainly don't need a גט get and you don't need מיאון. miun.
רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel say you need both. Okay, so now the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to continue. Let's take a look. איתמר. Itmar. מת
ונפלו לפני אחיו לייבום. Meis v'naflu lifnei achiv l'yibum. So this girl
who married herself off, okay, so what happened? So she married herself...
Okay,
so here's the dad.
Here's the dad, here's the girl. She goes ahead and she marries
herself off—the father didn't do it—to ראובן. Reuven. Okay. So רב ושמואל
Rav v'Shmuel say that means something, עולא Ulla says it doesn't mean
something. Then ראובן Reuven died and now you've got שמעון. Shimon. Okay.
So according to רב ושמואל, Rav v'Shmuel, when she did this, that
would have required גט get plus מיאון, miun, right? They would have
seen that even though she did it on her own. Now what
does שמעון Shimon have to do here? Is it a case of
ייבום, yibum, right? Okay, that's the question, right? So what's he going
to do? Of course, הלכתית, halachically, she might not have been married
to this guy at all. Okay, so what's שמעון Shimon required to
do? So let's take a look. מת ונפלו לפני אחיו לייבום. Meis
v'naflu lifnei achiv l'yibum. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna
amar Rav, so this is in the name of רב, Rav, so
this is obviously following רב ושמואל. Rav v'Shmuel. ממאנת למאמרו ואינה ממאנת
לזיקתו. Mema'enes l'mamaroh v'einah mema'enes l'zikasoh. She does מיאון miun if שמעון
Shimon does מאמר. mamar.
Remember what מאמר mamar is, that's when the brother-in-law does an act
of קידושין. kiddushin. So here she is, she's still a minor, there's
still a father, and שמעון Shimon goes ahead and now שמעון Shimon
does מאמר. mamar. שמעון Shimon does... So here there was one act
of קידושין, kiddushin okay, with the father, and he does now מאמר
mamar which is a second act of קידושין. kiddushin Okay. So if
after ראובן Reuven died שמעון Shimon did... If שמעון Shimon did מאמר,
ma'amar, then she has to do מיאון. mi'un. But she doesn't have
to do מיאון mi'un just because there's a זיקה. zika. Now we're
going to explain what this means. כיצד: Keitzad: עשו בה מאמר, Asu
bah ma'amar, if שמעון Shimon did מאמר, ma'amar, צריכה גט וצריכה חליצה
וצריכה מיאון. tzricha get vetzricha chalitza vetzricha mi'un. She needs all three,
okay, from שמעון. Shimon. Why does she need all three from שמעון?
Shimon? צריכה גט שמא נתרצה האב בקידושי שני. Tzricha get shema nitratza
ha'av bekiddushei sheini.
So following the same concern that whenever the minor who marries herself
off, the father might have agreed, so maybe we say like this,
maybe in this case the father didn't agree to the קידושין kiddushin
with ראובן, Reuven, okay, so this was nothing. But now that שמעון
Shimon did a מאמר, ma'amar, he did agree to the קידושין kiddushin
of שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so if he agreed to the קידושין kiddushin
of שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon has to give her a גט get
now. Everybody with me? If she really was married to ראובן, Reuven,
anyway I'm not going to deal with some hypotheticals. Anyway, if the
father agreed to the קידושין kiddushin, now that שמעון Shimon did, שמעון
Shimon is ראובן's Reuven brother, okay, then she's really married to שמעון
Shimon דאורייתא. de'oraita. If he didn't agree to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן's Reuven
out of the picture, so then the קידושין kiddushin is a real
קידושין דאורייתא kiddushin de'oraita and now she needs a גט get from
שמעון. Shimon. That's why she
needs a גט. get. צריכה חליצה שמא נתרצה בקידושי ראשון. Tzricha chalitza
shema nitratza bekiddushei rishon. But she also needs a חליצה chalitza because
maybe she had been married to ראובן, Reuven, okay, the father was
okay with the marriage with ראובן. Reuven. Now ראובן's Reuven dead, now
there's a real זיקה zika here to שמעון, Shimon, and now שמעון
Shimon really needs to do a חליצה, chalitza, okay? So שמעון Shimon
needs to do both a חליצה chalitza and a גט. get. A
חליצה chalitza because maybe she was married to ראובן, Reuven, a גט
get maybe she wasn't married to ראובן Reuven but now she's married
to שמעון Shimon because שמעון Shimon did a מאמר. ma'amar. Now, why
does she need
a צריכה מיאון שמא לא נתרצה לא בקידושי ראשון ולא בקידושי שני,
Tzricha mi'un shema lo nitratza lo bekiddushei rishon velo bekiddushei sheini, ואמרינן
קידושין תופסין באחותה. Ve'amrinan kiddushin tofsin be'achota. But she needs מיאון mi'un
because maybe the father didn't agree to either marriage and she's not
married to either guy and the גט get and the חליצה chalitza
is all meaningless. And to signal that all of that is really
meaningless, might be meaningless, it might be just a חומרא chumra and
it's not really דאורייתא de'oraita required, she does מיאון. mi'un. That shows
that the whole thing might really not be necessary, like we sort
of did before. Everybody with me more or less? Okay, fine. לא
עשה בה מאמר. Lo asa bah ma'amar. Now if שמעון Shimon did
not do מאמר, ma'amar, did not do a קידושין, kiddushin okay, what
are we left with? אינה צריכה אלא חליצה בלבד. Eina tzricha ela
chalitza bilvad. She only needs חליצה chalitza because what are the two
scenarios? One is the father was okay to her marriage to ראובן,
Reuven, okay, then there's a זיקה zika now to שמעון, Shimon, so
he does חליצה. chalitza. Scenario number two is the father wasn't okay
to her marriage to ראובן, Reuven, so then שמעון's Shimon out of
the picture. So if there was no מאמר, ma'amar, the only thing
relevant for שמעון Shimon to do is חליצה. chalitza. Now, מאי אמרת?
Mai amart? You should say one minute, maybe חליצה chalitza isn't enough.
תבעי נמי מיאון. Tiv'ei nami mi'un. Let's say that with the חליצה
chalitza she should need מיאון mi'un because remember the role of מיאון
mi'un here is to signal that this stuff might not be necessary,
right? So even if שמעון Shimon is just doing a חליצה, chalitza,
do a מיאון mi'un שמא יאמרו קידושין תופסין באחותה. shema yomru kiddushin
tofsin be'achota. Because people will say, ah, there's חליצה, chalitza, then she
was really married to ראובן. Reuven. And if she's really married to
ראובן Reuven and then there's a real זיקה zika to שמעון Shimon
and there's just חליצה, chalitza, people will think now that if שמעון
Shimon tries to marry her sister, it's not חל. chal. So maybe
you need to do a מיאון mi'un to signal that the חליצה
chalitza here might not have really been necessary. Okay, that would be
the question. But no, that's not a problem. הכל יודעים אחות חלוצה
דרבנן. Hakol yodim achot chaluza derabbanan. Everybody knows, everybody, I'm sure everybody
here knows that even though קידושין kiddushin isn't תופס tofes by a
wife's sister, even an ex-wife's sister, but if it's a חלוצה's chaluza
sister, קידושין kiddushin does work דאורייתא, de'oraita, only דרבנן derabbanan is it
forbidden. דאמר ריש לקיש De'amar Reish Lakish because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says in יבמות Yevamot in a case that we don't have to
get into, כאן שנה רבי. Kan shana Rebbe. From this משנה mishna
רבי Rebbe teaches us a משנה mishna over there in יבמות. Yevamot.
אחות גרושה דאורייתא. Achot grusha de'oraita. That the sister of a divorced
wife is דאורייתא de'oraita forbidden and therefore the קידושין kiddushin, doesn't take
effect. אחות חלוצה מדברי סופרים. Achot chaluza midivrei sofrim. The sister of
a woman that has only had חליצה, chalitza, so that's only forbidden
דרבנן derabbanan and דאורייתא de'oraita it would take effect. Okay, so if
there was only קידושין kiddushin, to ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon did
nothing, so now שמעון, Shimon, if this wasn't a good קידושין, kiddushin
the father was not okay with it, he does nothing. If it
was a good קידושין, kiddushin he does חליצה. chalitza. So all he
has to do is חליצה. chalitza. So the question is have him
also do מיאון mi'un to demonstrate that the חליצה chalitza might not
be required. And the answer is the whole purpose of demonstrating that
something might not be required was so people don't get confused that
maybe marriage to the sister would not be חל. chal. And here,
since it's only שמעון's Shimon חלוצה, chaluza, everybody understands that if שמעון
Shimon were to try to marry the sister, it would take. take
effect, so there's no need to signal that the חליצה chalitza is
a questionable חליצה. chalitza. All right, it's a little confusing, but you
get the idea. All right, anyway, bottom line is that was a
way of applying this case or case of יבום, yibum, but we're
back to רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel says this girl requires a
גט get and מיאון, miun, מיאון miun is to signal that the
גט get isn't necessarily required or might not be required, and in
the case of יבום, yibum, right, there's different scenarios of whether you
require all three, גט, get, חליצה, chalitza, and מיאון, miun, or whether
you require just חליצה. chalitza. Now the גמרא Gemara says the following:
הנהו בי תרי דהוו קשתו חמרא, hanu bei trei dehavu kashatu chamra,
תותי ציפי, tutei tzipi, there are two people that were drinking some
wine underneath like רש"י Rashi says like some type of a awning
בבבל beVavel in Bavel. שקל חד מינייהו כסא דחמרא, shakal chad mineihu
kasa dechamra, one of them took a cup of wine, יהב ליה
לחבריה, yehav lei lechaveirei, gave it to his friend, אמר amar and
he said, מקדשא לי ברתך לברי, mekadsha li bartech livri, let your
daughter be married to my son. Okay, so there they were they
were on a grand old time drinking wine and he gave him
a glass of wine and said, here, with this wine let your
daughter be married to my son. אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, Ravina, אפילו
מאן דאמר חיישינן שמא נתרצה האב, afilu man de'amar chaishinan shema nitratzei
ha'av, even when you say if the girl marries herself off we're
afraid that the father might have been okay with it, okay, so
here of course was the flip, the guy was accepting the wine
for his daughter, he was empowered to marry off his daughter, but
the guy who gave the glass of wine was marrying for his
son, he had not been empowered to do that for his son,
but let's say well maybe when the son finds out the son
will be okay with it, and maybe the same way we said
before the father would be okay and retroactively it would turn the
girl's the daughter's act into a meaningful act, here maybe afterwards the
son will be okay and it'll turn the father's act into a
meaningful act when he acted on behalf of his son. No. So
it says, ושמע מינה, ushma mina, I'm sorry, so the גמרא Gemara
says even according if you say that we're concerned the father would
be okay with the daughter's act, שמא נתרצה הבן לא אמרינן, shema
nitratzei haben lo amrinan, we don't say we're concerned maybe the son
found out and he became okay with it. Why? אמר ליה רבנן
לרבינא, amar lei rabanan leRavina, so anyway let's see what רש"י Rashi
says why: דשמא נתרצה הבן בקידושין שקידש לו האב שלא מדעתו, deshema
nitratzei haben bekidushin shekidesh lo ha'av shelo mida'ato, that the father did
married for the son without the son's input or awareness, לא אמרינן,
lo amrinan, we're not afraid that that the son became okay with
that. דאב בקידושי ברתו בכל דהו ניחא ליה, de'av bekidushai bito bechol
dehu nicha lei, דטב למיתב טן דו, detav lemeitav tan du, the
father has a lower standard being okay with some act that the
daughter did to marry herself off because fathers are trying to get
their daughters married off, okay, and you know, it's deemed more that
women will settle. אבל גברא דייק ונסב, aval gavra dayek venasiv, okay,
but a man he wants to be very discerning and exacting about
who he's going to marry. ובין אינו ברשות אביו לקדש לו אשה
שלא בשלוחו, ubein eino birshut aviv lekadesh lo isha shelo bishlucho, and
the father doesn't have the right and do it without being a
שליח. shaliach. So besides the question about the presumption of whether men
are more discerning or women are more discerning or who's trying to
marry off daughters and sons and so on, is also the point
that in this case you need real שליחות shlichut for him to
do it on behalf of the son even if the son was
okay with it retroactively, you have to be a שליח, shaliach, right?
We discussed before that when the daughter receives money maybe she didn't
she couldn't be a שליח, shaliach, anyway she was a minor, so
we discussed though that giving כסף קידושין, kesef kidushin, you know, you
could throw the כסף, kesef, you know, in the ocean and put
it on a rock and somehow if that's what the guy wants
it might count, okay, or the girl wants, whatever that might count.
Okay, but here to actually marry a the girl for the son
he would have to be a שליח. shaliach. So there's two reasons
why we won't say that if he was not designated as a
שליח. shaliach. Number one is we'll assume the son you know wants
to be much more certain about who he's marrying, and number two
is that דעת da'at isn't enough, you need real appointment of שליחות.
shlichut. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says: The son
is also a minor? The father? What? The brother has no more
interest than any other person? Exactly. That's the point. All right, yeah.
Okay. Well, right, he doesn't have any legal standing more than any
other person, but you might sort of say like maybe you know
there's a presumption that he would be okay with decisions his father
makes. I but you're right, he doesn't have a legal standing and
that's exactly it. Somebody goes ahead and does something for somebody else,
right, so it requires now you could do זכין לאדם שלא בפניו
zachin leadam shelo befanav but that's this is not so much זכין
zachin as we'll see in a minute. If the son is also
a minor clearly... No, actually if he's a minor then it certainly
wouldn't work because a minor cannot marry a woman. He would have
to have been an adult the son. Right, so this boy's an
adult but he has not designated his father. Correct. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה רבנן לרבינא, amar lei rabanan
leRavina, the rabbis say to Ravina, ודילמא שליח שוויה, udilma shaliach shaveih,
maybe he made him a שליח. shaliach. Now the question is when?
Are we afraid that he made him afterwards and retroactively? How would
that work? So maybe he made him a שליח shaliach from the
outset? I mean let's ask, let's find out, right? It's all a
question about like you know who are you know where are we
getting our our data our evidence from. Anyway let's be concerned, assuming
we can't figure know anything more about the case, if we went
if we saw the father do it, let's be concerned that that
might indicate that the father had been made. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, לא חציף אינש לשוויי לאבוה שליח. lo chatzif inish lishavei
l'avuah shaliach. People don't have the חוצפה chutzpah to make the father
a שליח shaliach to marry for them a woman for them. It's
so funny because you know you would think what do you mean
that's a חוצפה? chutzpah? You know the father now is in power
to do it. Father loves the idea. Great, I can marry off
my son. But again, it just shows the irony right because which
is that when the girl is doing it, she's a minor, she's
under the control of the father, it shows the father's power that
he's marrying off his daughter. But when the father is the son's
שליח, shaliach, the son is the one in power and the father
is just an agent of the son. So it shows a subservient
role to the son. Even though you could give the שליח, shaliach,
well the father being subservient to the son. Even though you could
give the שליח shaliach the discretionary power to choose, still fundamentally he's
doing a service for the son. And therefore it would be considered
like nobody would ever do that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ודילמא אצויי ארצי קמיה? v'dilma atzuy artzei kamei? But one minute, maybe
the son said to the father, oh you see that girl there,
I'd really love to marry her. And he was talking her up
to the father and then the father decided, oh great, I'm drinking
with with this girl's father, let me help out my son. So
maybe he was that's sort of like the case of the גמרא
Gemara before about שידוכים. shidduchim. Right, there was already a context where
you knew that the son might want it. Okay, now you could
read it the opposite, maybe the father was redding the שידוך shidduch
to the son. But either way there was a context where there
maybe was a presumption that the son would want it. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רבא בר שימי בפירוש אמר מר
דלא סבר לה להא דרב ושמואל. amar lei Rava bar Shimi befirush
amar mar d'lo savar lah l'ha d'Rav u'Shmuel. You know what, that
maybe makes it more of a question because that's sort of like
the case of שידוכים. shidduchim. But actually I know that רבינא, Ravina,
you know, you know that רבינא Ravina here disagrees with רב ושמואל
Rav u'Shmuel even in the case of the daughter. Even in the
case of the daughter we're not afraid that the father said okay.
So in a parallel case by the son we certainly won't be
afraid that the father said okay. If you said in the case
of the daughter that maybe the father afterwards was okay with it,
then maybe there would be something to be concerned about in this
שידוכים shidduchim case with the son. But bottom line we're פוסקן, paskening,
רבינא Ravina is פוסקן paskening that we're not even concerned in the
case of the daughter marrying herself off, so we're not going to
be concerned about the case of the father doing it for the
son. What was your question?
We're not concerned the son gave the father permission, right? We start
by... we're not concerned that the son gave the father permission because
it starts by the case that more people are concerned about, that
the father was okay when the daughter did it. רבינא Ravina isn't
even concerned about that case. So we're certainly not going to be
concerned about a case that the son gave the father permission. Okay,
but the גמרא Gemara starts trying to say maybe there could be
a way they could be comparable if there was some type of
a שידוך shidduch that preceded it. Okay, so now we're also seeing
the פסק psak question, because we're saying now that רבינא Ravina who
was a later authority, right, basically rejected רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel and
presumably even in a שידוך shidduch type of a context. Because now
we're talking in a שידוך shidduch type of a context. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. ההוא גברא דקדש בקישא דירקא בשוקא. hahu
gavra d'kadesh b'keisha d'yarka beshuka. There was a man who married a
woman with a bundle of vegetables in the marketplace.
Now, now apparently this woman was an underage girl, okay, with her
father. So אמר רבינא אפילו מאן דאמר חיישינן שמא נתרצה האב. amar
Ravina afilu man d'amar chayshinan shema nitratza ha'av. Even if you say
that we're normally concerned like רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel that maybe the
father was okay with it afterwards, הני מילי דרך כבוד. hani mili
derech kavod. That's only when the original קידושין was done in a
respectful manner. אבל הכא דרך בזיון, aval hacha derech bizayon, when the
original קידושין is done in a degrading manner, לא, lo, then we
would never be concerned that the father would be okay. So אמר
ליה רב אחא מדיפתי לרבינא בזיון דמאי? amar lei Rav Acha mi'Difti
l'Ravina bizayon d'mai? What made this degrading? אי בזיון דירקא אי בזיון
דשוקא? ei bizayon d'yarka ei bizayon d'shuka? Is it that it was
just a bunch of vegetables, like gave her some parsley or something,
I don't know, or was it because it was in the marketplace?
Which one would determine that we're not concerned that the father was
okay with it? נפקא מינה דקדש בכספא בשוקא nafka mina d'kadesh b'chaspa
beshuka because I can give you a case with one without the
other. Maybe he actually gave her money but it was in the
marketplace, או בקישא דירקא o b'keisha d'yarka or gave her a little
bundle of vegetables but it was בביתא, beveita, in the house. So
מאי? mai? So which one would be דרך בזיון derech bizayon that
we wouldn't have to be concerned about the father? אמר ליה אידי
ואידי דרך בזיון הוא. amar lei idei v'idei derech bizayon hu. Either
way would be דרך בזיון. derech bizayon. So now we're like limiting
the cases where we're concerned. One way we said earlier is maybe
according to רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel we're only concerned if there was
שידוכים shidduchim that preceded it. Now we're saying maybe we're not concerned
in case of בזיון bizayon and we'll have a broad definition of
בזיון. bizayon. You also have the position that we reject רב ושמואל
Rav u'Shmuel completely. Okay, now a third case. ההוא דאמר ליה לקריבאי,
hahu d'amar lei l'kriva'ei, oh this is the case we had before
you might remember in נדרים. Nedarim.
A man said let's marry off, I want to marry off our
daughter to my relative.
והיא אמרה לקריבה v'hi amrah l'krivah and she said no, we're going
to marry her off to my brother. He said I want to
marry her to my brother, she said... The wife said I want
to marry her to my brother. כפתיה עד דאמר לה תהוי לקרובה.
kafstei ad deamar lah tehvei lekrava. So she basically compelled him, you
know, and until he finally talked him into it, until he finally
conceded and said fine, she can marry your brother. Okay. עד דאכלי
ושתי, ad deachli veshashi, so then they were having a party. They
had a לחיים. lechayim. Okay, we decided she's going to marry the
wife's brother and they invited all their friends and they had a
לחיים. lechayim. She was engaged to the wife's brother. עד דאכלי ושתי
ad deachli veshashi and there they were eating and drinking, אתא קריביה
ata krevai his
brother came, באיגרא beigra up on the second floor, okay, וקדשה vekidsha
and they were he was up on the second floor with the
girl and gave her כסף קידושין. kesef kidushin. His brother, the one
that he initially had wanted. So if we say שמא נתרצה האב,
sheman nitratza haav, so here and especially in a case of שידוכין,
shiduchin, here we know the father had wanted her to marry his
brother and that's what happened in the end. In the interim, he
had given in to his wife, but are we going to say
that now he's going to go back to what he really wanted
all along and we're going to be concerned that now the father's
okay with it? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, we're not going to
be concerned in that case. כתיב שארית ישראל לא יעשו עולה. ksiv
she'erit Yisrael lo ya'asu avla. The remnant of Israel will not do
perversion ולא ידברו כזב velo yedabru kazav and will not speak falsehood.
So we are not concerned in this case of נתרצה האב. nitratza
haav. Even though that's originally what he wanted, once he agreed with
it to his wife that she was going to marry his brother,
we're not afraid he's going back. And not only did he agree
to his wife, excuse me, I should say it goes further because
he actually seems to have now, you know, agreed to the actual,
to the חתן, chatan, right? They made a party, they announced it,
like it says on the roof, but we announced it, but we
announced it. Okay, anyway,
so once actually he had made the promise and maybe even public
made public the promise, he's not going to go back. So we're
not now afraid that he was going to agree to what she
did with his brother. רבא אמר חזקה אין אדם טורח בסעודה ומפסידה.
Rava amar chazaka ein adam torach beseuda umasfida. No, no, no. It
wasn't just that he made the promise and announced it. They had
a party! Okay, so now he's not going to go and say
like, okay, forget the whole party, we have to have another לחיים
lechayim because she's now engaged to another guy.
Exactly.
Right. מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what's the difference? איכא בינייהו דלא טרח.
ika beinaihu delo tarach. They made the announcement, but they didn't yet
have the party. Okay. So that would be the case about are
you concerned now נתרצה האב? nitratza haav? Anyway, so the סוגיא sugya
ends with the question about I mean, we're going to have a
very related סוגיא sugya in a minute, but this סוגיא sugya ends
with the question about how do we פסקן? pasken? Do we פסקן
pasken that we're afraid the father said okay afterwards and then only
limiting it to cases where there was שידוכין, shiduchin, where it wasn't
דרך בזיון, derech bizayon, etc.? Or do we פסקן pasken sort of
like עולא Ulla and רבינא Ravina who basically said we completely reject
רב ושמואל? Rav uShmuel? Okay, so if you look at תוספות, Tosfos,
תוספות Tosfos says בפירוש אמר מר לא סבירא ליה דשמואל. beferush amar
mar lo sevira lei deShmuel. Okay, and תוספות Tosfos says like this,
if you go like five lines down in תוספות, Tosfos, the first
of the narrow lines, he says ופסק רב אלפס דצריך גט בשאילתות
דרב אחאי דהלכתא כרבינא. upasak Rav Alfas detzarich get bisheiltos deRav Achai
dehilchesa keRavina. We rule like רבינא. Ravina. זו בתרא, zu batra, he
was the later authority, the סוף הוראה sof horaah at the very
end of the גמרא Gemara period, היה, haya, ורב אשי נמי סבר
כוותיה ולא חיישינן שמא נתרצה האב. veRav Ashi nami savar kevastei velo
chaishinan sheman nitratza haav. You're not concerned with it. ואין צריך לא
גט ולא מיאון, veein tzarich lo get velo miun, ואפילו שידכו. vaafilu
shidchu. Okay, because that was the most, anyway, we sort of right,
discussing the son and the father doing it on behalf of the
son, we were talking about like a type of a שידוכין shiduchin
scenario. Okay, and it sounds like in the end we're saying we're
not concerned about it, even in a case of שידוכין, shiduchin, we're
never concerned. Okay, and then he says like
this. Now I'm going to skip a little bit, he says like
this. ואופסק בשאילתות דרב אחאי, veopasak bisheiltos deRav Achai, the line starts
with the word אחאי, Achai, it's about twenty lines down in the
narrow lines. Okay, he says בקטנה שהלך אביה למדינת הים. beketana shehalach
aviha lemedinat hayam. This is the case I told you. So number
one, if the father's around, we're not afraid that he agreed and
it's nothing. Let's say the father's on an overseas trip, he's been
away for years, שהיא יכולה להתקדש מדרבנן. shehee yachola lehitkadesh miderabbanan. She
actually can rabbinically, not דאורייתא deoraisa that we're never concerned about a
גט, get, but remember we were talking about מיאון miun and קידושין
דרבנן? kidushin derabbanan? When the mother married her, when she was emancipated,
let's say the father's alive but not around. Can we still have
the קידושין דרבנן kidushin derabbanan there in order to protect her? Right,
because the purpose of קידושין דרבנן kidushin derabbanan is the whole purpose
of קידושי קטנה kiddushei ketana and why we had to create a
דרבנן derabbanan form of it when there's no father is because the
family needed to make sure that the girl was looked after and
protected and had her future assured. So can we do that if
the father, right, can we do that if the father isn't around?
Okay, he's alive but not around. So here the same פסק psak
that is that if the father's around, we don't need anything, we're
not concerned with a גט, get, with מיאון miun or anything. Father
isn't around, we're asserting then there is a similar קידושי דרבנן kidushei
derabbanan that can take place. כדין יתומה דאין לאב דתקנו רבנן קידושין
משום הפקר, kedin yetoma deein leav detaknu rabbanan kidushin mishum hefker, so
she should not be taken advantage of. וזו שהלכה למדינת הים הרי
הוא כיתומה משום הפקר, V'zu shehalacha l'medinat hayam, hare hu k'yesoma mishum
hefker, we're afraid she'll be taken advantage of. So in that case,
we allow for there to be a קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin derabbanan. רב
מנחם מיאוני Rav Menachem me'yuni אינו מודה בדבר. eino modeh badavar. He
does not agree. ומעשה אירע U'ma'aseh ira באחד שהלך לארץ רחוקה, b'echad
shehalach l'eretz rechoka, he went away to a faraway land, והניח בת
קטנה, v'hiniach bat ktana, he left a small daughter, and maybe there
was a wife or whatever, but it doesn't matter, technically only the
father has control. ונישאת הבת, V'nis'at habat, and the daughter was married
off. ואסר רב מנחם מיאוני לקיימה, V'asar Rav Menachem me'yuni l'kayma, and
רב מנחם Rav Menachem said you're not allowed, stay, guy can't stay
married to her, this guy that the parent, that the mother married
her off to. Why? And he had a new reason. Not only
is it, we don't believe that it's a קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin derabbanan,
but a new problem. חיישינן שמא יקדשנה אביה לאיש אחר במקום שהוא.
Chayshinan shema y'kadshana aviha l'ish acher bimkom shehu. Maybe the father, who's
over in Japan, in the meantime has married her off to some
other man. So how can she now be married to a man
here, right, whether there is a קידושין דרבנן kiddushin derabbanan or not?
What about, what we don't know what the father is doing over
in Japan. And then he gets into a whole debate with רבינו
תם. Rabbeinu Tam. And רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says if you're afraid
about that, let's say the father dies in Japan. She should never
be able to marry anybody because maybe the father married her when
he wasn't around. So we're not concerned what the father does when
he's not around, we're not afraid that it happened. Anyway, it's very
fascinating to see that there was a real need, this ties into
the first תוספות Tosafot of the פרק. perek. There was a real
need to ensure that the girls were married off at a young
age, and even though the גמרא Gemara says you're not supposed to
do it. And now we see that even if the father wasn't
around, wanted to make sure that they were protected and married off.
So on the one hand, if the father is around and she
goes ahead and does something, it's meaningless, and there's no need for
גט get or מיאון me'un or whatever. That's the פסק psak at
the end. But if the father is far away, there was a
question that maybe we needed to assume that there is some type
of קידושין דרבנן kiddushin derabbanan that she or the mother can do
in order that her interests will be protected. Okay, so we will
continue with this.